# 这就是五仁月饼的料 把它拌匀了
This is the filling for Wuren mooncakes. Let's mix it well.
# 看着啊怎么打月饼
Watch carefully, this is how we shape the mooncakes.
# 左一下右一下
Left and right
# 看到没有 三下
Only three times!
# 老饭骨的月饼
Mooncakes by Laofangu
# 这五仁月饼是怎么做出来的
How do we make this Wuren mooncake?
# 咱们今天就一步一步给大家展示一下
We will show you guys step by step
# 告诉我们的网友们粉丝们
To teach our followers and fans
# 您看这儿一共有这么多种干果
Look at all these dried fruits and nuts
# 它叫五仁 但是其实咱们这里
It is called Wuren, five nuts, but we have more than five
# 不光是搁了五种仁
types of nuts here
# 您看核桃仁 杏仁 西瓜子仁
We have walnuts, almond, watermelon seeds
# 葵瓜子仁 南瓜子仁  花生米
Sunflower seeds, pumpkin seeds and peanuts
# 这好东西啊 还有芝麻仁
These are the good stuff. And also sesame seeds
# 这些刚才我已经全都烤了一遍
I have roasted all of them just now
# 而且不止是五仁
Not only do we have the "five nuts"
# 这边咱还有辅料
Here are some other ingredients
# 葡萄干 这是糖冬瓜
Raisins, candied wintermelon
# 橘丁 口味酸甜特别提味
Candied orange chunks. It is sweet and tangy and will enhance flavors
# 咱们先把馅和一下 就这么处理
Let's mix all of the ingredients
# 咱们把核桃仁掰一下
Break up the walnuts into smaller pieces
# 因为它整个的有点大
Since a whole walnut is too big
# 咱把杏仁也切一下
Also cut up the almonds
# 五仁月饼是一个传统的老月饼
Wuren mooncake is very traditional
# 北方月饼基本上五仁的居多
It is a very popular type in the northern areas
# 大爷最爱吃的是五仁月饼
Daye's favorite is Wuren mooncake
# 第二选择呢是豆沙月饼
Second favorite is mooncake with red bean paste filling
# 第三选择是枣泥月饼
Third favorite is mooncake with date paste filling
# 您上回跟我说您还爱吃什么
You told me another one last time
# 咱老北京的 自来红自来白
Our traditional Beijing ones, Zilaihong (natural red) and Zilaibai (natural white)
# 青红丝 一般现在搁的都少了
Qinghongsi, which is less common in the mooncakes these days
# 好多网友对于青红丝的制作不知道
Many of our followers don't know the process of making Qinghongsi
# 其实它用什么做成的
It is actually made out of tangerine peels
# 它是用橘子皮做的 没错 特别香
It is very fragrant
# 您看看咱这料 丰富多彩
Look at all the ingredients
# 这就是五仁月饼的料 把它拌匀了
This is the filling for Wuren mooncake. Let's mix it well
# 我这还一个秘密武器
I have another secret weapon
# 腌的玫瑰花瓣 还有点白糖
Cured rose petals with white sugar
# 这五仁就不一样了
This takes the mooncake to another level
# 今天老饭骨又加以创新了
Laofangu is innovating the Wuren filling
# 现在能闻到淡淡的玫瑰香气
I can smell the scent of the rose petals already
# 大爷帮我个忙 您看那一瓶 酒
Daye, can you help me with the Baijiu over there?
# 大爷给我来一点酒
Add a little wine
# 高度的清香型白酒
Hard liquor with light aroma
# 这搁酒是一个什么样的作用
Why are we putting in Baijiu?
# 一个是提香
It brings out more aroma
# 一个是防腐
And help preserves the mooncake longer
# 而且柔软 它不发干
It will also make the filling softer and less drying
# 咱这儿还有香油 倒里边
Now in goes some sesame oil
# 这的是传统的东西
This is the traditional stuff
# 您看现在这个仁儿是散着的
Now the filling is still very loose
# 加点白豆沙
Add in some lima bean paste
# 就因为加上这个 它才黏糊了
So that the filling can stick together better
# 然后大爷 我刚才还准备麦芽糖了
Daye, I also prepared some maltose earlier
# 我拿过来 好勒
Ok, I will bring it over
# 再来点麦芽糖 行了够了
And a little bit maltose syrup. Ok, that's enough
# 咱们现在里边还得加点糕粉
We are also putting in some Gaofen, steamed sticky rice flour
# 糕粉来拌到里边让它馅好成型
So that it shapes better
# 糕粉咱们在网上也能买到
You can find Gaofen pretty easily online these days
# 月饼馅里边所有的食材
In fact, all of the ingredients for the filling
# 都在网上都可以买到
can be found online
# 给它和的粘稠能粘到一块
Mix it so that the ingredients can stick together
# 一会咱们给它分一下
We will divide the filling later
# 咱们一会做的饼是一百克的饼
We are making 100g mooncakes today
# 所以咱们皮和馅的比例是五五
So the ratio of the wrapper and the filling is 1:1
# 这就行了 五十克
This is enough, 50g
# 馅分好了 咱们和面
We have divided the fillings. Now let's mix the dough
# 然后把这糖先下去 一百五十克
First sugar, 150g
# 以前的皮儿里边不加这个（鸡蛋）
We didn't add eggs before
# 咱这一百五十克的糖
For 150g of sugar,
# 一个半鸡蛋 然后咱再加点水
We will add one and a half eggs and then some water
# 先打一下
Mix them together
# 把糖给它打化了
Until the sugar dissolve
# 咱把麦芽糖倒进去 二十克
Then add 20g of maltose
# 师父您看现在开始倒油了
Master, look, now we are adding oil
# 这油不能一次倒进去 得分批倒
Add the oil in batches
# 花生油就行了
Peanut oil will do
# 一斤面搁两百克花生油
For 1 Jin (500g) of flour, add 200g of peanut oil
# 这就好了
That's it
# 咱们把这富强粉倒进去 一斤富强粉
Then some bread flour. 500g of bread flour.
# 咱们这为什么叫提浆月饼
Why did we use to call this Tijiang (golden syrup) mooncake
# 提浆是怎么来的
The Tijiang part
# 其实就是咱们以前的白砂糖
Is because sugar didn't use to be
# 没有现在的这么干净
as clear
# 所以就把这熬成糖浆
So we made it into syrup
# 现在咱们这糖浆都可以了
Now the quality of sugar is better
# 所以不用去熬这个转化糖浆了
We don't have to make the inverted sugar syrup
# 过去的提浆月饼皮也硬 馅也硬
Both the filling and the wrapper of the Tijiang mooncakes are harder
# 这回咱们加入鸡蛋就松软多了
But since we added the eggs, it will be softer and fluffier
# 还有蛋香味
And has the aroma from the egg
# 把它和滋润了
Knead the dough until smooth
# 然后咱们把它搁在盆里边饧一下
Then left it in the pot to rest
# 大爷咱这面饧的差不多了
Our dough is ready
# 咱们开始把它分剂子
Let's divide it
# 咱们做一百克的饼 五十克一个的剂子
Since our mooncakes are 100g each, we will divide the dough into 50g pieces
# 皮五十克 馅五十克 齐了
50g of wrapper and 50g of filling
# 包月饼了 咱把这个皮给摁开了
Let's wrap! Spread out the wrapper
# 把咱们刚才分好的馅包进去
And put the filling in
# 吃五仁月饼吃的就是馅
The most important part of a Wuren mooncake is the filling
# 咱们在家包
If we wrap it at home
# 五五也可以 四六也可以
The ratio can be 1:1 or 2:3 for dough and filling
# 看看这手法 这手得这样捂着
Look at the method, fold it with your hands
# 慢慢往里边一团 跟包菜团子似的
And slowly close it up, like making a veggie wrap
# 大师姐这小手巧
Dashijie's hands are very limber
# 您别夸我了 夸我一会包不上了
Stop praising me, what if I mess up later
# 这就好了 包好一个
That's it, the first one
# 看着啊 怎么打月饼
Watch carefully, how to shape it
# 咱们打点糕粉 什么叫糕粉大师姐
Now let's spread some Gaofen. -What is Gaofen, Dashijie?
# 其实就是熟面要细
It is just very fine cooked flour
# 如果没有糕粉 咱们把面蒸熟也可以
If you don't have Gaofen, you can use steamed flour
# 看着啊 这月饼怎么来的
Look, this is how mooncakes are made
# 给它压好了
Press it in
# 跟这压一下 为了让它平一下
Press it again so it levels
# 然后您看着
Then look
# 左一下右一下
Left and right
# 看看 老饭骨月饼
Look, mooncake by Laofangu
# 再来一块 二伯给照精细点啊
Another piece. Er Bai, can you film it closer?
# 我顾这头你顾那头
I'll film this side and you will film it from the other side
# 现在工厂有机械压
Now there are machines to make mooncakes in factories
# 但是咱们老饭骨的全是手工的
But all Laofangu mooncakes are handmade
# 手打五仁月饼
Handmade Wuren mooncakes
# 那时候我们一打打多少 十万块
How many did we use to make back then? 100,000 pieces in a row
# 摔月饼也得有把子力气 好家伙
To hit the mooncake press mold you need lots of strength
# 摔一天胳膊受不了
Your arms will be sore after a day
# 那时候我们都是排队
We used to take turns
# 一个人团馅  一个人揪剂儿 一个人砸
One person would mix the filling, another one would make the wrapper and one more person would shape the mooncakes
# 这三人一天 比如说弄两千块
In a day, three people needed to make, let's say 2000 pieces
# 不打完两千块不让下班 还有专门烤的
You couldn't get off work until you finish 2000 pieces. There was also someone who bakes the mooncakes
# 这得稳准狠
You have to be precise and strong
# 大爷师父您看
Da Ye and master, look
# 今天咱们打的这个饼是一百克的
Today the mooncakes are 100g each
# 这是一百克模子
Since the mold is for 100g (mooncake)
# 咱们还给网友准备了五十克的模子
We have also prepared 50g mooncake molds
# 它稍微薄一点 它好烤一点
So that it's thinner and bakes faster
# 这样容易磕出来
It comes out of the mold easier
# 我颠着都比较有重量 压手
It feels quite hefty
# 这样磕出来才好使
It is handy to make mooncakes (to be hefty)
# 烤箱刚才我预热了一下 二百度
I just preheated the oven to 200 degree Celsius
# 然后先烤十分钟
Let's bake it for 10mins first
# 咱们十分钟到了
That's 10mins
# 刷点蛋液 让它上色 刷的要匀
Brush a layer of egg wash so that it will become golden brown, and make sure to brush evenly
# 走 二百度再烤十分钟
Another 10mins at 200 degree
# 一共烤二十分钟就出来了
A total of 20mins
# 好了 咱们可以出锅了
OK, the mooncakes are ready
# 大爷看
Look, Da Ye
# 好吃的月饼来了
Here comes the tasty mooncakes
# 咱们掰一个 来这馅多的给您吃
Let's split it. Here is a piece with more fillings
# 这个块大的给我师父吃
The bigger piece for my master
# 现在刚烤出来的还有点发干
It is a bit dry since it is fresh out of the oven
# 返两天油它就油润了
You can seal it up and wait for two days, then it will be oilier
# 您赶紧尝尝怎么样
Try it
# 来 我给您拿着
Here, I will hold the camera
# 每次都让我先尝
I'm always the first to taste
# 先尝有责任 我得先说
I have the responsibility to review first
# 好吃吗 好吃
How is it? -It is very delicious.
# 有很多人可能对五仁月饼不太了解
Many people might not know Wuren mooncake very well
# 几种仁的合成 它就产生不同的香味
The combination of different nuts generates various aromas
# 有的可能会做 里边还要加上冰糖块
Some people put in rock sugar cubes
# 咱们为什么不建议加
But we don't recommend it
# 有些老年人不注意 咔
Since some elderlies might not be aware of the rock sugar
# 把牙给硌坏了
And break their teeth accidentally
# 我本身就喜欢吃甜的
I have a sweet tooth
# 五仁的 枣泥的 豆沙的
Wuren, date paste, red bean paste
# 这是我喜欢吃的东西
These are the fillings I like
# 那时候做这些月饼的时候
In the old days when they made mooncakes,
# 那些老师傅是实实在在 是货真价实
the elder masters were honest and true. They made real good mooncakes.
# 我们今天老饭骨
Today at Laofangu
# 传承老一辈的这种手艺
We are passing on the traditional method
# 皮酥 馅香 甜度适口 原料丰富
Flaky wrapper, fragrant filling, the right amount of sweetness and rich ingredients
# 谢谢大爷 谢谢朝辉
Thank you Daye! Thank you Zhaohui!
# 吃月饼
Time to eat the mooncakes!